Benjamin Franklin Papers Part 5 -- Letters to Franklin 1779 December-1780 December Mss.B.F85inventory05
American Philosophical Society
- Letters to Benjamin Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 May 23; A.L.S. 3p.; Cooper, Samuel. Boston
    Arrival of the Marquis de la Fayette in the "Hermione"; advantages to be looked for from the presence of this frigate. High estimate in which the Comte d'Estaing is held; services he has rendered the cause.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, VIII, 455; Bigelow, VII, 60).
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 May 23; A.L.S. 2p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Humble apologies made by him to the Grand Facteur; no result so far. News from St. Eustache of the embarrassing position of the English in those waters. Opposition to Amsterdam's request.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 May 24; A.L.S. 2p.; Duclos, -----. Corbeny
    Asking Franklin's favor on behalf of his relative, Davesne, who desires to pursue his military career in America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 May 24; A.L.S. 1p.; Depotien Duboishalbrand, —, chevalier. Rabastens
    Arrived from Baltimore with a hundred and thirty-two dollars in Pennsylvania money; desires to know where he can get its equivalent in French money; all he has left after a twenty months' imprisonment in New York.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 May 25; Read, J.K. Richmond, Va
    Introducing Joseph Mayo, a gentleman of the first character and fortune in Virginia.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 May 26; A.L.S. 2p.; Reallon, Joachim. Saint Jean-de-Luz
    Agreed with Richard Graham and Co. to take charge of the sloop "Canister" from Dumfries, Va., to France; was taken prisoner, carried to England and lately exchanged; the agreement was that he should be paid twenty pounds in case he was taken; desires to know how he is to procure the said sum.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 May 26; A.L.S. 2p.; Torris, John. Dunkirk
    Furnishing further evidence of their just and undeniable claim to the cargo of the "Aurora"; entreats Franklin to hasten her condemnation, as well as that of several other prizes.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 May 26; A.L.S. 1p.; Allaire, Peter. Paris
    Franklin to deliver to the bearer the paper of [James's] powders and [William] Eden's letters to [the Earl of] Carlisle.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 May 27; A.L.S. 1p.; Adams, James. "Mill Prison," Plymouth
    Bears a Master's Warrant in the service of the United States; taken prisoner eighteen months before and carried to England; the prospect of an early exchange has wholly vanished; hopes that his rank in the navy will entitle him to Franklin's notice, and to a small sum of money.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 May 27; A.L.S. 1p.; Duvivier, Pierre-Simon-Benjamin. Paris
    The medals ordered by Franklin are finished; only waits for the names of the recipients to engrave them thereon.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 May 29; A.L.S. 1p.; Pougens, Marie-Charles-Joseph, chevalier de. Paris
    Begs for an interview.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 May 29; A.L.S. 1p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Publication of Gen. Clinton's letter. Two bills drawn on Mr. Laurens in the name of Congress; injury to American credit owing to the non-arrival of the gentleman; M. de Neufville's promise to pay one.
    (In French, partly in cipher and deciphered.)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 May 29; A.L.S. 1p.; Landais, Capt. Pierre. L'Orient
    Stating his determination to retake the command of the ship "Alliance," unless Franklin has some express authority for depriving him of it; his responsibility to those who entrusted the vessel to his charge.
    Printed in Hale's "Franklin in France," I, 329.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 May 29; A.L.S. 2p.; John de Neufville and Son. Amsterdam
    Enclosing certain bills of exchange drawn on Henry Laurens, Esq., and discussing the necessary provisions to be made for their payment, in case Mr. Laurens fails to appear in a fortnight.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 May 30; L. 1p.; "Your Ould Friends in Broad St." London
    Enclosing a printed account of certain war-like inventions discovered by John Cross, an ingenious English engineer, who offers his services to France and America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 May 30; A.L.S. 2p.; Digges, Thomas. London
    Requests Dr. Franklin to procure, if possible, some written instrument whereby the baggge of Dr. Upton Scott of Annapolis, Md., may be secure from seizure, should the vessel upon which he embarks for home be seized by an American cruiser; Dr. Scott's character.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 May 31; D.S. Cha[rle]s Thomson, Sec[retar]y. 1p.; The Continental Congress
    Draughts drawn by John Adams and his Secretary, Mr. Dana, to be paid by the Minister at Versailles until further notice.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 May 31; D.S. Cha[rle]s Thomson, Sec[retar]y. 1p.; The Continental Congress
    Commending the action of the Minister at Versailles in relation to prizes taken by Captain John Paul Jones, but released by the Court of Denmark. Accompanied by the preceding instructions in regard to the salaries of John Adams and Mr. Dana.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 May 31; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Lafreté, Jean-Jacques de. Paris
    Charged by Madame [De] Lafreté to remind Franklin not to lose a certain letter, but to put it in his pocket the first time he cornes to see her.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 May 31 (?).; A.L.S. 2p.; Landais, Capt. Pierre. L'Orient
    Duplicate of XVIII, 108, with the additional remark that both officers and crew desire him to return to his command, as well as a copy of a letter from the Admiralty Office in Philadelphia, sent to him as Captain of the "Alliance."
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 May; A.L.S. 4p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Cause of the breach between himself and the French Ambassador. Reasons why he wishes to be the first to speak to Mr. Laurens. No truth in the report that any Dutch city has concluded a treaty with the United States. His opinion on the question of the Dutch ship taken by Mr. Jones.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 June 1; D. S. Cha[rle]s Lee, Sec[retar]y. 3p.; The Board of Treasury
    An order for carrying out Resolutions of Congress of May 19, 1780, drawing on Dr. Franklin for $25,000.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 June 2; A.L.S. 2p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Both bills drawn on Mr. Laurens to be accepted by Messrs. de Neufville. Concerning the Dutch ship taken by Mr. Jones.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 June 2; A.L.S. 6p.; John Diot and Co. Morlaix
    Surprised that the papers relative to the "Betsey" never reached him; a blunder on the part of the Admiralty Office; difficulties in the way of selling the two other prizes, "Peter" and "Friendship." Safe arrival of the "Black Princess" after a thrilling encounter with three English frigates, who used glass bottles with which they rammed their guns; no man wounded thus could possibly recover. Disagreement between Capt. Macatter and the Commissary of the Marine at Morlaix; the letter threatens to retain the privateer and throw the Captain into jail; appeals to Franklin for redress.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 June 3; D.S. 1p.; Favre, Jean Louis. Havre
    Certifying that Samuel Nuttle, an American, served on board his frigate as first lieutenant and fulfilled all his duties with the greatest exactitude; thinks his forty years' experience on the sea entitles him to the position of Captain.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 June 4; A.L.S. 2p.; Gérard, Conrad Alexandre. Versailles
    Concerning a box of furs belonging to Mr. [Robert] Keith, carried by mistake to St. Pierre, and the greater part subsequently ruined or lost, begs Franklin to dispose of the remainder to the best possible advantage.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 June 4; A.L.S. 4p.; Besson, George Leopold. Montéliard
    Would like to be supported for the remainder of his days.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 June 4; A.L.S. 2p.; Caffiéri, Jean Jacques
    Has just heard that the Congress, in recognition of the services rendered by the late Count Pulaski; have resolved to erect a monument to his memory, to be executed by a French artist. Reminds Franklin of his promise to give to him the execution of any monuments ordered.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 June 5; A.L.S. 3p.; John Diot and Co. Morlaix
    Renewing their entreaties for the speedy release of the "Black Princess"; if Franklin does not take Capt. Macatter's part with the French Ministry, she is like to be detained much longer; incredible harm this delay causes her owners; the Captain's offense in enlisting French sailors was one of ignorance, which he endeavored to correct by their immediate release.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 June 6; A.L.S. 2p.; Cadet de Vaux, Antoine-Alexis. Paris
    Inviting Franklin to be present at the opening of l' Ecole de Boulangerie; he and M. Parmentier will make speeches and they will consider themselves honored by Franklin's presence.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 June 6; A.L.S. 3p.; Wulffen (Wolff), Jean Henry, baron de. Paris
    Has abandoned everything for the United States; weakened by wounds, he was taken prisoner by the English and treated in the most inhuman manner; desires to return at once to America; demands his Captain's pay for the last eight months, the amount that his rations would have cost and a new uniform.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 June 6; A.L.S. 3p.; Nuttle, Samuel. Havre-de-Grace
    Is an American who desires employment in his country's service; served as First Lieutenant on board the French ship "Josephine"; begs Franklin to procure him a dispensation from the Minister, in order that he may be admitted as Captain in the French merchant service.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 June 6; A.L.S. 3p.; Torris, John. Dunkirk
    Acknowledging Franklin's letter of the 27th ult. with the enclosed judgement, giving up the ship "Aurora" and condemning (under some hard restrictions) the cargo; makes some observations on the justice of this decision and asks for information on one or two points; encloses a paper respecting the cargo and its owners.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 June 6; A.L.S. 1p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    No news of Mr. Laurens. Absence of the French Ambassador.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 June 7; A.L.S. 1p.; Butler, John. Passy
    Has just arrived from London, and desires an interview.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 June 7; A.L.S. 3p.; Torris, John. Dunkirk
    Showed Capt. Downlin Franklin's letter concerning the "Peter" and the "Friendship"; defends the Captain against the suspicions therein entertained; hopes the enclosed proofs [5 p.] will convince Franklin of the genuineness of these prizes and determine their condemnation. Trusts Franklin will see justice done to Capt. Macatter and his brave boys who fought three Guernsey privateers for nine hours and cut everyone to pieces. Capt. Ryan's distinguished conduct in the "Fearno(ugh)t".
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 June 9; A.L.S. 1p.; Marky, J. Paris
    Desires to learn the safest way to convey a letter to Charles Country, Maryland.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 June 10; A.L.S. 2p.; Dumouriez, -----. Cherbourg
    Forwards a package of letters from American prisoners in England; has redirected the envelope without breaking the seal, so that Franklin may the better judge of their genuineness.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 June 10; A.L.S. 2p.; Wulffen (Wolff), Jean Henry, baron de. Paris
    Begs that the enclosed letters may be forwaded to America; is grateful for the twelve louis; needs thirty more by the eighteenth. As soon as his wounds permit, expects to reimbark for America where he looks forward to shedding his blood once more in such a glorious cause.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 June 11; A.L.S. 3p.; Torris, John. Dunkirk
    Bemoans the detention of the "Black Princess"; the opportunities she is missing of making prizes and distressing the enemy, and the great expense of her maintenance; will answer for the innocence in this matter of the good-natured and brave Capt. Macatter; accuses the Commissary at Morlaix of jealousy and of exceeding his prerogatives. Encloses a copy of the testimony of Capt. Macatter and crew.
    (4 p. In French.)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 June 12; A.L.S. 5p.; Rainey, John. Amsterdam
    Concerning Continental Loan-Office Certificates in his possession which are greatly reduced in value, and which he is anxious to dispose of in Holland, France or Spain; asks Franklin's advice in the matter, as such a step might prove detrimental to the credit of the United States. Report from London of Lord G. Gordon having gone up to the Parliament Houses with 5,000 men and a petition against the Popery Bill, etc. The prevailing opinion is that if Charleston can hold out, the English will withdraw their troops from the United States.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 June 12; A.L.S. A[lexander] Gillon. 2p.; The Commodore of the Navy of the States of South Carolina. L'Orient
    Has the direction of one vessel for the service of South Carolina and is about to buy others; asks Franklin to aid him in procuring the necessary officers and seamen and to grant passes to such as he may engage; believes such assistance to be due him, in spite of the uniform opposition his efforts have met with in Europe; expects to purchase the prize-ship, "Serapis." Apologizes for interfering, but is strongly of the opinion that Capt. Landais should either be allowed to assume the command of the "Alliance" or be shown the order from Congress forbidding such a step.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 June 13; A.L.S. 1p.; ----- Depotot and ----- Desgrange. Versailles
    Asking for a commission in the United States army; desire merely the rank of Lieutenant, which they have held in France for five years, and to have their traveling expenses paid.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 June 13; A.L.S. 1p.; Johnson, Joshua. Nantes
    Encloses letters just arrived from New London.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 June 13; A.L.S. 1p.; Russell, James. London
    Acknowledging Franklin's favor of the 20th ult. directed to Messrs. Stanbury, Grove and Russell; Mr. Stanbury is at Bath but expects to be in London in a month, at which time the letter shall receive an answer.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 June 13; A.L.S. 3p.; Nesbitt, Jonathan, & Co.
    The disturbances on board the "Alliance" in consequence of Capt. Landais's assuming the command of that frigate; the Captain's probable motives in taking this step; his own private sentiments on the matter.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 June 13; L.S. 2p.; Jones, Capt. John Paul. L'Orient
    On his arrival found that Capt. Landais, encouraged by Mr. Lee and Mr. Gillon, had raised a party spirit on board the "Alliance"; steps he took to meet such a move; this very day during his absence, Capt. Landais went on board the "Alliance" and declared his intention of keeping the command by force, if necessary; no steps can be taken without written orders from Franklin; encloses letter from the Secretary of the Admiralty, upon which Captain Landais bases his pretentions. The armament of the "Ariel" rapidly advancing; expects the two ships to carry to America the articles immediately wanted; clothes more important than muskets.
    Printed in part in Hale's Franklin in France, I, 335.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 June 13; A.L.S. 1p.; Lee, Arthur. L'Orient
    The passport given him by Franklin has expired and is now useless; will be obliged for another one.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 June 13; A.L.S. 2p.; Lebègue de Presle, Achille-Guillaume. Paris
    Promised him any literary news which came in his way; quotes from a letter just received from London, giving an account of a house which had conductors, being struck by lightning, account of a cure for scurvy which Capt. Cook ascertained from a Dutch sea captain; this consisted in scraping a plant called conferva from the ship's side and eating it as a salad.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 June 14; A.L.S. 2p.; Wharton, Samuel. L'Orient
    Complaints about Capt. Landais and the original officers of the "Alliance" refusing to give up command of the vessel to Capt. Jones. Capt. Landais reported reasons for doing so. Thinks the latter is being made use of by Franklin's personal enemies. Suspects Mr. Lee is at the bottom of the affair.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 June 14; A.L.S. 2p.; Wharton, Samuel. L'Orient
    Concerning the atrocious conduct of Capt. Landais in taking possession of the "Alliance"; partisans of Landais assert that Franklin assumed a power unwarranted by his Ministerial office in suspending Landais and giving the command to Capt. Jones; thinks that Landais is being made use of to create confusion and delay the public stores; the facts would not authorize his declaring Mr. Lee to be at the bottom of the affair, but thinks there is little doubt that he employed every indirect means in his power to that end.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 June 14; A.L.S. 2p.; Landais, Capt. Pierre. L'Orient
    Has taken command of the "Alliance"; in accordance with the advice of the principal Americans and the desire of his officers and crew; in obedience to the enclosed letter from the Secretary of the Honorable Navy Board [1 p.], is determined to carry her to America; desires that Franklin will have the officers and crew paid their prize money and forward his despatches that he may fulfil the orders of Congress.
    Printed in Hale's "Franklin in France," I, 333.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 June 15; A.L.S. 2p.; Cossoul, -----. Nantes
    Writes on behalf of his friend Mr. Watson, relative to certain notes drawn on Franklin but unfortunately lost in Boston by Mr. Foster; asks that all precautions may be taken to prevent their being paid to anyone but Mr. Watson.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 June 15; A.L.S. 3p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Giving a complete account of M. Corn. Van Oudermeulen, who has a secret of some importance to communicate to Franklin. Sir Joseph Yorke's denial of the genuineness of the published letter of General Clinton.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 June 15; A.L.S. 2p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Awaiting his decision relative to the vessel "Flora". Will make good use of Franklin's letter to he owners of American privateers. Delighted with his reflections on the subject of Gen. Clinton's letter.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 June 15; A.L.S. 1p.; Rainey, John. Amsterdam
    Reports received of the guards having fired on the people in London and killed many. A ship from St. Eustatia reports the English fleet defeated in another battle with the French fleet.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 June 15; A.L.S. 4p.; Moylan, James. L'Orient
    Was informed that a number of sailors belonging to the service of the United States, and now under the command of Capt. J. P. Jones, had engaged with Commodore Gillon of South Carolina and had been sent to some town in Holland; had them arrested and lodged in the prison at l'Orient; his authority for this step; threats made against him, by Commodore Gillon; if such desertions are permitted, there will not be sufficient sailors left for the transportation of the supplies for the United States.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 June 16; A.L.S. 3p.; Reimers, Nic Barth. Orleans
    Is a subject of the Empress of Russia; begs for a situation in the service of the United States.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 June 16; A.L.S. 1p.; Landais, Capt. Pierre. L'Orient
    Wrote on the 14th inst. that he had reassumed the command of the "Alliance". Wishes orders in regard to powder and cannon on board; has repeatedly written for the prize-money due his people, but has never had the honor of a reply. Encloses copy of his commission with the necessary documents to show that he has the stole right to command the "Alliance". Ready to receive any orders or despatches for America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 June 17; A.L.S. 1p.; Engelhard,-----. Brumath
    Studied at Strasburg; was Assistant Surgeon in the Royal Swiss Guards at Paris; desires the promise of a sure position in America and his passage over paid.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 June 18; A.L.S. 1p.; Marky, J. Irish Seminary
    Expressing his appreciation of Franklin's offer to have his letters conveyed to America; sends the packet with their duplicates.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 June 19; A.L.S. 1p.; Chrestien and Co. Paris
    Concerning an order received from M. Chardron, Agent for Massachusetts, to furnish ninety pieces of cloth for the United States.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 June 19; A.L.S. 2p.; Chaumont, Jacques-Donatien Le Ray de
    Enclosing a letter from M. de Montplaisir who was entrusted with the forwarding of the squadron under Commodore Jones; from this letter Franklin may see that Mr. Lee and Commodore Gillon have publicily encouraged the reprehensible conduct of the crew of the "Alliance"; suggests that this letter may be communicated to M. de Vergennes, who may think it expedient to propose to these gentlemen to keep away from l'Orient, at least until the "Alliance" is ready to sail.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 June 19; A.L.S. 2p.; Torris, John. Dunkirk
    Enclosing the declaration [2 p., in French] made by Capt. Thos, Byrne, lace of the schooner "Peter," before a Notary Public in London, which effectually removes the suspicions Franklin entertained of this prize being not really English; hopes there will be no further delay in her condemnation. Has not yet heard of the release of the "Poor Princess" and her brave people.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 June 20; A.L.S. 1p.; Reine, — de. Versailles
    Sends Franklin a bottle of Rake which they use to make their punch and which they prefer to rum or tafia.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 June 20; A.L.S. 1 p.; Lafayette, Marie-Adrienne-Françoise de Noailles de (marquis' wife).
    Desires news of Charlestown, [S.C.,] as well as the truth concerning the reported defeat of the English and the death of Gen.Clinton; as a good American herself, and the wife on one whom America has honored, begs that this favor may be granted her.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 June 20; L.S. 1 p.; Lambert, Sir John. Paris
    Desired by Mr. James Cuming, of Philadelphia, to request him to stop payment on two bills, lost or mislaid.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 June 20; A.L.S. 2 p.; Auer, Deacon M. Ebingen, Würtemberg
    Refers to fourfold letter (see LIX, 35 and 37), sent in September, 1779, relative to estate of Catharine Hocklerin's son in the care of Christian Schneider, in Germantown.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 June 21; A.L.S. 2 p.; Joseph Gardoqui and Sons. Bilbao
    Announcing the arrival of the "General Pickering" from Salem; the Captain, having a good deal of room on board to spare, desires to offer it to Franklin for the freighting of any goods to America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1780 June 21; L.S 4p.; Jones, Capt. John Paul. L'Orient